Guide to the Everett and Evelyn Ortner papers and photographs ARC.306
Brooklyn Historical Society
Everett and Evelyn Ortner papers and photographs
1873-2012
1965-2008
Brooklyn Historical Society
Back to the City Conference
Brownstone Revival Committee
Ortner, Evelyn
Ortner, Everett
ARC.306
51.85 Linear Feet in 79 boxes, 8 film canisters, 1 flat file drawer, and 1 personal computer
0.065 Megabytes in 2 digital files.
The collection contains the papers and photographs of Everett and Evelyn Ortner, dating from 1873 to 2012. It documents the Ortners personal and professional lives, especially their involvement in the historic preservation movement and Brooklyn cultural organizations. It includes the records of the Brownstone Revival Committee and Back to the City Conference. The collection's photographs extensively document 19th century buildings in Brooklyn and Manhattan, especially the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Estate of Everett and Evelyn Ortner, 2014.
Biographical note
Everett H. Ortner was born in Lowell, Massachusetts, on August 25, 1919. When he was child his family relocated to Brooklyn, New York. He attended P.S. 99, Jamaica High School, and James Madison High School, from which he graduated in 1935. He attended the University of Arkansas in Fayetteville, graduating with a bachelor's degree in 1939. He then entered the U.S. Army as an officer and trained at Fort Benning, Georgia. In 1945 he was deployed to the European theater of World War II, where he was wounded in action and taken prisoner. He received a Bronze Star Medal for his service in 1948. After the war he was employed as an editor at Popular Science magazine from 1952 until his retirement in 1985.
Evelyn F. Gelbman was born in Manhattan on July 4, 1924. She was raised in the north Bronx and attended Washington Irving High School, graduating in 1942. She then attended Hunter College, graduating in 1952. Later she studied design at Parsons School of Design and Pratt Institute, and historic preservation at Columbia University. She was employed as an interior designer from the 1950s to the 2000s, and was a design columnist for the Brooklyn Heights Press and Homeowners How To Handbook. She was also the Director of Facilities and Collections for the New York Chamber of Commerce and Industry from 1979 to 1984, where she curated the organization's archives and portrait collection.
The Ortners married in 1953. They lived in the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn in the 1950s and early 1960s. In 1963 the couple purchased an 1882 four-story brownstone at 272 Berkeley Place in the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn. This would be the catalyst for their involvement in the "Brownstone Revival" movement. The Ortners soon became active in a variety of community organizations. They lobbied local banks to provide mortgages to prospective Park Slope home-buyers at a time when lenders had "red-lined" the neighborhood. According to the Park Slope Civic Council, "they also encouraged the Brooklyn Union Gas Co. (now National Grid) to purchase and transform a dilapidated brownstone on Berkeley Place into a modern two-family home featuring a variety of gas appliances." These buildings became known as "Cinderella homes" and were used in advertising to entice new residents to the neighborhood. The couple were also a leading force in the designation of the Park Slope Historic District in 1973.
Starting in the 1960s, Everett was involved with the Park Slope Civic Council (as photographer and vice-president), the Park Slope Betterment Committee (founder), the Brownstone Revival Committee of New York (co-founder and president), the Back to the City Conference (co-founder and president), the Montauk Club (board member and president), the Brooklyn Historical Society/Long Island Historical Society (board member and vice-president), and Preservation Volunteers (co-founder with Evelyn). Evelyn was involved with the Brooklyn Academy of Music (board member), Brooklyn Museum (president of the Community Committee), the St. Ann Center for Restoration and the Arts (co-founder and chairman of the board), Brooklyn Stained Glass Conservation Center (vice-president and board member), the Long Island Historical Society (member), the Montauk Club (board member), the Victorian Society in America (New York Chapter, board member and secretary), the Fine Arts Federation of New York (board member), the Brooklyn Center for the Urban Environment (board member), Develop Don't Destroy Brooklyn (board member), and Preservation Volunteers (co-founder with Everett).
The Ortners were the recipients of numerous awards and honors, including the Brooklyn Union Gas Company's Cinderella Award (1978), the Preservation League of New York State's Excellence in Historic Preservation Award (2002), and the New York Landmarks Conservancy's Lucy G. Moses Preservation Leadership Award (2005).
Evelyn Ortner died at 272 Berkeley Place on September 19, 2006 at age 82. Everett followed on May 22, 2012, at age 92.
Sources:
Harris, Elizabeth A. "A Couple Who Gave Brownstones New Life," New York Times, June 4, 2012.
Hartocollis, Anemona. "Evelyn Ortner, 82, a Booster of Brooklyn Brownstones, Dies," New York Times, September 22, 2006.
Hevesi, Dennis. "Everett Ortner, Leader in Brooklyn Brownstones' Revival, Dies at 92," New York Times, May 26, 2012.
Park Slope Civic Council. "Remembering Everett Ortner," last modified July 13, 2012. "http://parkslopeciviccouncil.org/remembering-everett-ortner/">http://parkslopeciviccouncil.org/remembering-everett-ortner/.
EGO school work, resumes, correspondence, and ephemera, 1945-1958; Everett and Evelyn Ortner papers and photographs, ARC.306, Box 1, Folder 2; Brooklyn Historical Society.
Who's Who - Biographical, 1984-2009; Everett and Evelyn Ortner papers and photographs, ARC.306, Box 19, Folder 4; Brooklyn Historical Society.
EHO curriculum vitae and award correspondence, 2006-2009; Everett and Evelyn Ortner papers and photographs, ARC.306, Box 19, Folder 21; Brooklyn Historical Society.
Conditions Governing Access
Papers and photographs open to researchers without restriction. The collection's audiovisual and digital files are not currently accessible.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the papers and photographs of Everett H. Ortner (EHO) and Evelyn G. Ortner (EGO), dating from 1873 to 2012. It documents the Ortners personal and professional lives, especially their involvement in the historic preservation movement and Brooklyn cultural organizations.
Series 1: Evelyn G. Ortner personal papers contains files relating to EGO's education, interior design career, employment at the New York Chamber of Commerce and Industry, curation of the Fulton Ferry Firehouse exhibit, and her role as Chairman of the Board of Directors of the St. Ann Center for Restoration and the Arts.
Series 2: Everett H. Ortner personal papers contains files documenting the early life, education, military career, and professional career of EHO.
Series 3: Everett and Evelyn Ortner personal papers documents the professional, social, and familial lives of the Ortners, dating from 1900 to 2010. It includes an assortment of correspondence, clippings, photographs, ephemera, memorabilia, digital files, and other materials.
Series 4: Brooklyn and Historic Preservation photographs contains photographs related to Brooklyn and historic preservation in a variety of formats, dating from circa 1880s to 2000. Formats include prints, slides, negatives, and glass plate negatives. The series includes original photograghs by EHO, copy photographs of historic images used by EHO in lectures, and a small amount of original photographs taken by other photographers.
Series 5: Brooklyn and Historic Preservation lectures contains files on Brooklyn and historic preservation lectures, dating from the 1970s to 2006. The lectures were primarily delivered by EHO. The files include lecture notes, slide lists, transcripts, clippings, photographs, flyers, and audio cassette recordings.
Series 6: Brooklyn and Historic Preservation general files is comprised of assorted files relating to Brooklyn (history and culture) and the historic preservation movement that were collected by the Ortners, dating from circa 1880 to 2008. The files include publications, typescripts, correspondence, photographs, posters, notes, and other materials.
Series 7: Brownstone Revival Comittee records contains files relating to the Brownstone Revival Committee (BRC) (later Brownstone Revival Coalition), dating from 1967 to 2008. It includes organizational records, lecture and workshop files, copies of the Brownstone calendar, and issues of the organization's publication, The Brownstoner.
Series 8: Back to the City Conference records contains records relating to the Back to the City Conference (BTTC), dating from 1973 to 1992. It includes the records of the organization (Board of Directors files) and files relating to individual conferences.
Series 9: Brownstones and Historic Preservation clippings contains clippings relating to brownstones and the historic preservation movement, including the Brownstone Revival Committee (BRC), Back to the City Conference (BTTC), and the Brooklyn Union Gas Company's Cinderella project, dating from 1966 to 1985.
Series 10: Brownstone correspondence consists of correspondence relating to brownstones and the urban historic preservation movement, especially in the Park Slope neigborhood of Brooklyn, dating from 1965 to 2005. It includes several organizations, such as the Park Slope Betterment Committee, the Brownstone Revival Committee, and the Back to the City Conference.
Series 11: Brooklyn Union Gas Company - Cinderella projects documents the Brooklyn Union Gas Company's Cinderella program. The series consists of publications, correspondence, films, histories on the program and the company, and ephemera, dating from 1968 to 2008.
Series 12: Historic District Designation Reports contains New York City Historic District Designation Reports (1969-1973) and one map of historic locations in the Greenpoint and Williamsburg neighborhoods of Brooklyn (2005).
Series 13: Brooklyn and Manhattan postcards contains Brooklyn and Manhattan postcards and a small amount of other postcards and tradecards (Rising Sun Stove Polish and Paine's Funiture Manufactory) collected by EHO, dating from 1873 to 2007.
Related Materials
Downtown Brooklyn Development Association records (1979.021)
Robert Vadheim Brooklyn neighborhood renewal and development collection (1987.002)
Robert Vadheim collection on the renovation of St. Ann and the Holy Trinity Church (1988.014)
Back to the City collection (1991.036)
Eastern Parkway Coalition records (2007.016)
H. Dickson McKenna collection (ARC.060)
Brooklyn Chamber of Commerce publications (ARC.165)
Brooklyn neighborhood associations and civic organizations publications (ARC.167)
Other Finding Aids
A portion of the collection's photographs have been digitized and cataloged at the item level and are available via our in-house photographic database in our library's reading room.
272 Berkeley Place (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Acetate film; Architectural drawings; Architecture |x Conservation and restoration; Artifacts (object genre); Atlantic Avenue (New York, N.Y.); Audiocassettes; Banks and banking |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Boerum Hill (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Bridge (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Buildings, structures, etc.; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History; Brownstone buildings |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Buildings |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Calendars; Carroll Gardens (New York, N.Y.); Civic improvement |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Civic leaders |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Clinton Hill (New York, N.Y.); Clippings (information artifacts); Cobble Hill (New York, N.Y.); Color slides; Community activists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Correspondence; Dinners and dining |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Discrimination in mortgage loans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Downtown Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Dye diffusion transfer prints; Ephemera; Festivals |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Flatbush (New York, N.Y.); Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Fulton Ferry Landing (New York, N.Y.); Gelatin dry plate negatives; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Grand Army Plaza (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Greenpoint (New York, N.Y.); Historic preservation |v Congresses; Historic preservation |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Interior design |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Lantern slides; Long Island, Battle of, New York, N.Y., 1776; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Manuscripts (document genre); Negatives (photographic); Newsletters; Newspapers; Park Slope (New York, N.Y.); Photographs; Picture postcards; Postcards; Posters; Programs (documents); Prospect Heights (New York, N.Y.); Prospect Lefferts Gardens (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Prospect Park (New York, N.Y.); Prospect Park South (New York, N.Y.); School yearbooks; Stained glass windows |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Typescripts; VHS (TM); Waterfronts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.); Back to the City Conference; Brooklyn Academy of Music; Brooklyn Botanic Garden; Brooklyn Historical Society (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Museum; Brooklyn Union Gas Company; Brownstone Revival Coalition (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brownstone Revival Committee; Columbia University. Graduate School of Architecture, Planning, and Preservation; Green-Wood Cemetery (New York, N.Y.); Hunter College; Jamaica High School (New York, N.Y.); James Madison High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Long Island Historical Society; McKenna, H. Dickson; Montauk Club of Brooklyn; National Grid Company; New York Chamber of Commerce and Industry; Ortner, Evelyn; Ortner, Everett; Park Slope Betterment Committee (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Park Slope Civic Council; Popular Science Publishing Company; St. Ann and the Holy Trinity (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); St. Ann Center for Restoration And Arts; United States. Army; University of Arkansas, Fayetteville; Victorian Society in America
- Series 1: Evelyn G. Ortner personal papers, 1911-2002; 43745
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains records relating to Evelyn G. Ortner (EGO), dating from 1911 to 2002. It documents her education, interior design career, employment at the New York Chamber of Commerce and Industry, curation of the Fulton Ferry Firehouse exhibit, and her role as Chairman of the Board of Directors of the St. Ann Center for Restoration and the Arts. Additional files related to EGO's work as a board member and volunteer at other Brooklyn cultural institutions (Brooklyn Museum, Long Island Historical Society, Brooklyn Botanic Garden, etc.) can be found in Series 3: EHO and EGO personal and Series 6: Brooklyn and Historic Preservation general files.
  Arrangement
  The series is organized into five sub-series:
  Sub-series 1.1: EGO school papers
  Sub-series 1.2: Interior Design
  Sub-series 1.3: New York Chamber of Commerce and Industry
  Sub-series 1.4: Fulton Ferry Firehouse exhibit
  Sub-series 1.5: St. Ann Center for Restoration and the Arts
  - Sub-series 1.1: EGO school papers, 1938-1978; 43415; 0.3 Linear Feet in six folders
    The sub-series contains files relating to EGO's time as a student at Washington Irving High School, Hunter College, Parsons School of Design, Pratt Institute, and Columbia University, dating from 1938 to 1978. It includes course work, ephemera (commencement programs and song books), correspondence, transcripts, and administrative records. She studied romance languages at Hunter College, design at Parsons School of Design and Pratt Institute, and historic preservation at Columbia University.
    Arranged chronologically.
    - EGO school documents, 1938-1942; 43423 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      General
      Includes Washington Irving High School and PS 80 (Bronx)
    - EGO school work, resumes, correspondence, and ephemera, 1945-1958; 43424 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Includes resumes
    - EGO Hunter College, 1952; 43425 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - EGO Theory Visual Form class work, 1958; 43426 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - EGO Columbia Graduate School, 1974-1978; 43427 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - EGO Columbia paper, 1975-1976; 43428 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sub-series 1.2: Interior Design, 1959-1993; 43405; 7 Linear Feet in twelve folders, four oversize folders, one slide box, and one small box
    The sub-series contains records relating to EGO's career as an interior designer, dating from 1959 to 1993. It includes design plans, business correspondence, clippings, photographs, and samples of fabric, tile, and wood.
    She authored two decorating columns, one titled "The Decorating Workshop" in the Brooklyn Heights Press from 1961 to 1962, and one titled "Decorating Your Home" in the Homeowners How To Handbook from 1976 to 1980. Clippings and typescripts of these articles are available in the sub-series.
    Of note are files relating to the design of apartments at 116 Central Park South and 45 Gramercy Park North, and one box of fabric, tile, and wood samples for the apartment at 45 Gramercy Park North.
    - Joseph Freitag Interiors - Frigidaire Colonnade Kitchen (1 of 2), 1959; 43429 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Includes photographic prints and transparencies
    - Joseph Freitag Interiors - Frigidaire Colonnade Kitchen (2 of 2), 1959; 43408 (Cabinet Flat file A, Drawer 1)
      Oversize folder containing drawings and designs for the following: Dr. Rosa Lenz (15 West 12th Street), Miles Davis (230 East 125th Street), Mr. and Mrs. T. Newhouse, and the National Home Furnishings Show (Kitchen - Model House)
    - Joseph Freitag Interiors - 116 Central Park South (1 of 2), 1959-1962; 44123 (Box 73, Folder -)
      Includes photograph
    - Joseph Freitag Interiors - 116 Central Park South (2 of 2), 1959-1962; 43407 (Cabinet Flat file A, Drawer 1)
      Oversize folder containing blueprints and designs
    - Interior design negatives and slide, circa 1960s; 44023 (Box 51, Folder 4)
    - Brooklyn Heights Press "The Decorating Workshop" articles and ideas (2 folders), 1961; 43430 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
      Includes photographs, full issues of Brooklyn Heights Press, and lecture notecards
    - Brooklyn Heights Press - Full issues featuring EGO's "The Decorating Workshop" column, 1961-1962; 44129 (Box 73, Folder -)
      Oversize
    - Kitchens, etc. designed by EGO slides, 1963-1975; 44079 (Box 67, Folder 9-11)
    - Lindenauer Apartment - 45 Gramercy Park North (folders 1-4 of 5), 1974-1993; 43431 (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
      See also box 4, which contains samples of fabric, tile, and wood
    - Lindenauer Apartment - 45 Gramercy Park North (5 of 5), 1974-1993; 43409 (Cabinet Flat file A, Drawer 1)
      Oversize folder containing architectural drawings and wallpaper samples
    - Lindenauer Apartment - 45 Gramercy Park North - Fabric, tile, and wood samples, circa 1974-1985; 43450 (Box 4, Item -)
    - Homeowners How To Handbook articles by EGO (2 folders), 1976-1980; 43783 (Box 39, Folder 13-14)
  - Sub-series 1.3: New York Chamber of Commerce and Industry, 1918-1985; 43416; 2.25 Linear Feet in fifteen folders and one oversize folder
    The sub-series documents EGO's employment as Director of Facilities and Collections of the New York Chamber of Commerce and Industry, where she was employed from about 1979 to 1984. It includes correspondence, memoranda, reports, clippings, photographs, and ephemera dating from 1918 to 1985. EGO managed the sale of portions of the Chamber's art collection.
    - Chamber of Commerce of the State of New York - Bulletins and reports, 1918, 1932, 1947; 43432 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - New York Chamber of Commerce - Civic Group Conference on Increased Subway Fare, 1947; 43433 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - New York Chamber of Commerce organizational report and merger clipping, 1947, 1972; 43434 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Chamber of Commerce of the State of New York - Tribute to John D. Rockefeller program and photographs, 1950; 43435 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Chamber of Commerce of the State of New York - Miscellaneous (two folders), 1960s-1980s; 43436 (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
    - New York Chamber of Commerce and Industry - 65 Liberty Street sale, 1966, 1984-1985; 43437 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - New York Chamber of Commerce ephemera, 1968-1980s; 43438 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - EGO Chamber of Commerce business cards, name plate, and badge, circa 1980; 43439 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - New York Chamber of Commerce and Industry - Notes, correspondence, and clippings (2 folders), 1979-1981; 43440 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
    - New York Chamber of Commerce and Industry, 1979-1984; 43441 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - New York Chamber of Commerce - A. Carmelita correspondence, 1980-1981; 43442 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - New York Chamber of Commerce and Industry - Chamber orientation program and photographs of Pan Am Building and Manhattan waterfront, 1982; 44105 (Box 72, Folder -)
    - New York Chamber of Commerce and Industry event and building photographs, 1982; 43443 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - New York Chamber of Commerce and Industry building - Great Hall photographs and negatives, circa 1982; 43444 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Sub-series 1.4: Fulton Ferry Firehouse exhibit, 1911-1976; 43448; 2.9 Linear Feet in two folders and one oversize folder
    The sub-series contains files relating to the Fulton Ferry Firehouse exhibit that was produced by EGO in 1976. It includes exhibition planning files, early 20th century city reports on the waterfront, copy prints of the waterfront, and ephemera, dating from 1911 to 1976. The copy prints were derived from negatives produced by the Department of Ports and Terminals from circa 1890 to 1913. Related copy prints, negatives, and slides can be found in Series 4: Brooklyn and Historic Preservation photographs.
    - Fulton Ferry Firehouse exhibit (1 of 2), 1911-1976; 43449 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Fulton Ferry Firehouse exhibit (2 of 2), 1911-1976; 49409 (Box 75, Folder -)
    - Fulton Ferry Firehouse exhibit, 1975; 43451 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Includes set of reproduction photographs of Fulton Ferry and Brooklyn waterfront
  - Sub-series 1.5: St. Ann Center for Restoration and the Arts, 1977-2002; 43452; 3.4 Linear Feet in ten folders, one oversize folder, and one audio cassette
    The sub-series documents EGO's work as the Chairman of the Board of Directors of the St. Ann Center for Restoration and the Arts. It includes Board of Directors files, ephemera, photographs, and clippings, dating from 1977 to 2002. Of note are reports and other files on the restoration of the Church of St. Ann and the Holy Trinity building and its stained glass windows.
    - Church of St. Ann and the Holy Trinity restoration and The St. Ann Center for Restoration and the Arts (1-3 of 4 folders), 1977-1999; 43453 (Box 5, Folder 2-4)
    - Church of St. Ann and the Holy Trinity restoration and The St. Ann Center for Restoration and the Arts (4 of 4 folders), 1997; 49404 (Box 75, Folder -)
      Oversize. Window restoration plans.
    - St. Ann Center for Restoration and the Arts - Board of Directors files (1-2 of 4 folders), 1980-1984; 43454 (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
      Includes photographs
    - St. Ann Center for Restoration and the Arts - Board of Directors files (3-4 of 4 folders), 1980-1984; 43455 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - St. Ann Center for Restoration and the Arts and the Brooklyn Stained Glass Conservation Center, 1980-2002; 43462 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - The Arts at St. Ann's ephemera, 1983-1985; 43607 (Box 23, Folder 12)
    - WOR interview with EGO on St. Ann's audio cassette, 1985; 44100 (Box 52, Folder -)